Evelyn Kirmse University of Arizona Centennial Collection 1885-1986 (bulk 1930-1986)
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections
Evelyn Kirmse University of Arizona Centennial Collection 1885-1986 (bulk 1930-1986)
MS 460
Kirmse, Evelyn Jones, 1900-1986
Research files, documents and printed material, 1885-1986 (bulk 1930-1986). The bulk of the material is notes and printed material taken and collected while researching the writing of a history of the University of Arizona. Notes are hand-written, typed and on note cards. The collection also contains drafts and outlines for sections of the history as well as correspondence and progress reports. There is information on a variety of subjects including notable individuals, campus buildings and sites, colleges and departments, events and thematic topics like athletics, women, salaries, student activism, extension work and academic freedom.
7 linear ft.
University of Arizona Libraries, Special Collections University of Arizona PO Box 210055 Tucson, AZ 85721-0055 Phone: 520-621-6423 Fax: 520-621-9733 URL: http://speccoll.library.arizona.edu/
Restrictions
There are no restrictions on this collection.
Biographical Note
Evelyn Jones Kirmse was born in 1900 in Baltimore, Maryland and died in 1986 in Tucson, Arizona. Kirmse received her bachelors and masters of art degrees from George Washington University in the 1920’s. She came to the University of Arizona in 1929 as Dean of Women. Kirmse served as a State Board of Regents member from 1951 to 1959 and was elected the first women president of the board in 1958. In 1980, she received an honorary degree from The University of Arizona. She co-chaired the Centennial Committee that planned the 100th anniversary celebration for UA in 1985. As Special Assistant to University President John Schaefer she worked on creating a history of the University which was not completed before her death. In 2006 Kirmse was honored with a donation to the Women’s Plaza of Honor on the UA campus.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into 2 series
Series I: University of Arizona History.
Series II: Book development and compilation.
Scope and Content Note
Research files, documents and printed material, 1885-1986 (bulk 1930-1986). The bulk of the material is notes and printed material taken and collected while researching the writing of a history of the University of Arizona. Notes are hand-written, typed and on note cards. The collection also contains drafts and outlines for sections of the history as well as correspondence and progress reports. There is information on a variety of subjects including notable individuals, campus buildings and sites, colleges and departments, events and thematic topics like athletics, women, salaries, student activism, extension work and academic freedom.
Access Terms
Kirmse, Evelyn Jones, 1900-1986"
University of Arizona. College of Medicine - History
University of Arizona - History
University of Arizona - Regents
University of Arizona - Facilities
University of Arizona - Presidents
University of Arizona - Students
Container List
- Series I: University of Arizona History
  This series is arranged alphabetically and contains notes and printed material taken and collected while researching the writing of a history of the University of Arizona.
  - Subseries 1: Buildings and Campus Sites
    - Arizona State Museum, 1893-1953 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    - Buildings, 1820-1980 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Cactus Garden and Planting, 1906-1940 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Colleges Historical, 1891-1981 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Fine Arts, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Foundations –"Seed Money", 1979 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Foundations –“Growths (Campus etc.)”, Early 1900-1979 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    - Library, 1972-1977 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Mining Interests, 1863-1940 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Multiple Mirror Telescopes, 1979 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Music, 1929-1985 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Phi Lambda Phrateres, 1977 (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Planetarium, 1975 (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Presidents House, 1936-1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - UA Cemetery, 1930 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Subseries 2: College of Medicine
    - Bradford, 1975-1978 (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Interview Medical Colleges, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 17)
    - Medical College Clippings (Some from McKalip Files) (Box 1, Folder 18)
    - Medical College Dr. Melick, 1962-1979 (Box 1, Folder 19)
    - Medical College Material from Dr. Melicks files (1 of 2), 1954-1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Medical College Material from Dr. Melicks files (2 of 2), normal= "1954/1977">1954-1977 (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Medical College Medical School Committee, 1958 (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Medical College Peacock (1 of 2), 1958-1979 (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Medical College Peacock (2 of 2), 1958-1979 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Medical School Location fight, 1959-1975 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Medical School Holsclaw, Etc., 1978 (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Medicine, 1916-1979 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - The Coming of Medical Education to Arizona by William R. Mathew’s, c. 1968, 1946-1979 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Subseries 3: Events
    - 1885 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - 1900-1913 (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - 1914-1918 (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - 1920’s, 1920-1929 (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Between Wars, 1918-1929 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - 1930’s (1), 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - 1930’s (2), 1930-1939 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - 1940’s, 1940-1949 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Post World War II, 1939-1940; undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - 1950's, 1950-1959 (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - 1958 (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - 1960's, 1960-1969 (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - 1962 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - 1963 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - 1964 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - 1965 (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - 1966 (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - 1967 (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - 1968 (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - 1970’s (1), 1970-1979 (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - 1970’s (2), 1970-1979" (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - 1980-1985 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Subseries 4: Notecards
    - Various Subjects on events, places, and people. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Various Subjects on events, places, and people. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Various Subjects on events, places, and people. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - Various Subjects on events, places, and people. (Box 9, Folder 1)
    - Various Subjects (1), undated (Box 10, Folder 1)
    - Various Subjects(2), undated (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Subseries 5: Presidents
    - Atkinson, Alfred, 1958; undated (Box 11, Folder 1)
    - Burgess, Paul, 1936-1937; 1975; undated (Box 11, Folder 2)
    - Cummings, Byron, 1972; undated (Box 11, Folder 3)
    - General information, undated (Box 11, Folder 4)
    - Harvill, Richard, 1965; 1981; undated (Box 11, Folder 5)
    - Hunt, Marvin (1), 1973-1985; undated (Box 11, Folder 6)
    - Hunt, Marvin (2), 1973-1975; 1985; undated (Box 11, Folder 7)
    - Koffler, Henry, 1983; undated (Box 11, Folder 8)
    - McCormick,James Byron, 1958-1973; undated (Box 11, Folder 9)
    - Schaefer, John (1), 1976-1985; undated (Box 11, Folder 10)
    - Schaefer, John (2), 1976-1985; undated (Box 12, Folder 1)
    - Shantz, Horner L., 1936; 1973; undated (Box 12, Folder 2)
    - Von Kleinsmid, Rufus B., 1920; 1964; undated (Box 12, Folder 3)
  - Subseries 6: Regents
    - Arizona Broad of Regents Compilation of Board Policies, 1966 (Box 12, Folder 4)
    - Bilby, Ralph, 1969-1981 (Box 12, Folder 5)
    - Bimson, Walter, 1953-1973 (Box 12, Folder 6)
    - Campbell Rudy, 1974-1979 (Box 12, Folder 7)
    - Capin,Esther, 1977-1985 (Box 12, Folder 8)
    - Chambers, George, 1903-1977 (Box 12, Folder 9)
    - Chandler, Thomas, 1976-1982 (Box 12, Folder 10)
    - Christy, Margaret, 1971-1976 (Box 12, Folder 11)
    - Dunseath, James Elliott, 1971-1978 (Box 12, Folder 12)
    - Federhar, Andrew, 1978-1979 (Box 12, Folder 13)
    - Handy, John C., 1976 (Box 12, Folder 14)
    - Individuals/Misc., 1817-1983 (Box 12, Folder 15)
    - Jacome, Alex, 1955-1980 (Box 12, Folder 16)
    - McNulty, James F. Jr., 1980-1986 (Box 12, Folder 17)
    - Molloy, John F., 1977-1978 (Box 12, Folder 18)
    - Morris, Samuel H., 1969-1970 (Box 12, Folder 19)
    - Organization, 1865-1980 (Box 13, Folder 1)
    - Organization Etc. (1 of 2), 1860-1980 (Box 13, Folder 2)
    - Organization Etc. (2 of 2), 1860-1980 (Box 13, Folder 3)
    - Paris, Gordon, 1975-1978 (Box 13, Folder 4)
    - Patterson, Dwight, 1975-1980 (Box 13, Folder 5)
    - Payne, William G. M.D., 1962-1979 (Box 13, Folder 6)
    - Samaniego, Mariano, 1975; 1978; undated (Box 13, Folder 7)
    - Senator Kret, Dave, 1974 (Box 13, Folder 8)
    - Scott, Winfield, 1972-1973; undated (Box 13, Folder 9)
    - Scott, The life and times of Winfield Scott, undated (Box 13, Folder 10)
    - Warner, Carolyn, 1975-1976; undated (Box 13, Folder 11)
    - Woods, Sidney, 1971-1979; undated (Box 13, Folder 12)
  - Subseries 7: Various subjects
    - Artist series, 1891-1980 (Box 14, Folder 1)
    - Athletics, 1885-1982 (Box 14, Folder 2)
    - Comparisons, misc., 1886-1977 (Box 14, Folder 3)
    - Castro, Raul, 1975-1978 (Box 14, Folder 4)
    - Dean of Women, undated (Box 14, Folder 5)
    - Discrimination and civil rights, 1930-1976 (Box 14, Folder 6)
    - Early days of higher education in Arizona (1), undated (Box 14, Folder 7)
    - Early days of higher education in Arizona (2), undated (Box 14, Folder 8)
    - Early days of higher education in Arizona (3), undated (Box 15, Folder 1)
    - Early days of higher education in Arizona (4), undated (Box 15, Folder 2)
    - Early days of higher education in Arizona (5), undated (Box 15, Folder 3)
    - Extension work, 1959-1968 (Box 15, Folder 4)
    - Faculties (Academic Freedom, Salaries, etc.), 1930-1983 (Box 15, Folder 5)
    - Governors (Various), 1958-1980 (Box 15, Folder 6)
    - Minority programs, 1970-1983 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Minority programs, 1970-1983 (Box 15, Folder 7)
    - Mortar Board, 1977-1982 (Box 16, Folder 1)
    - Pyle, Howard, 1958-1976 (Box 16, Folder 2)
    - Preparatory Dept., 1861-1973 (Box 16, Folder 3)
    - Senate athletics, 1978-1979 (Box 16, Folder 4)
    - Statistics, 1967-1979" (Box 16, Folder 5)
    - Student Activism, 1970's (Box 16, Folder 6)
    - Student Life and Activities, 1920-1971 (Box 16, Folder 7)
    - Unsorted, 1891-1985 (Box 16, Folder 8)
    - Women, 1918-1980 (Box 16, Folder 9)
    - World War II, 1940's (Box 16, Folder 10)
    - World War II, 1940's (Box 16, Folder 11)
    - Harvill TV-radio interviews, undated (Box 16, Folder 12)
- Series II: Book Development and Compilation
  This series is arranged alphabetically.
  - Correspondence (Various general), 1973-1985 (Box 17, Folder 1)
  - Draft/outlines, 1864-1980 (Box 17, Folder 2)
  - Illustrations, 1825-1979 (Box 17, Folder 3)
  - Interviews, 1913-1984 (Box 17, Folder 4)
  - Introd., undated (Box 17, Folder 5)
  - Marshall Townsend (corr.) A Press, 1975-1981 (Box 17, Folder 6)
  - Notes (Lamp in the Desert), 1973 (Box 17, Folder 7)
  - Outlines, undated (Box 17, Folder 8)
  - Outlines/chronology, 1863-1977 (Box 17, Folder 9)
  - Recommendations, 1965-1976 (Box 17, Folder 10)
  - Schaefer-Reports, 1973-1977 (Box 17, Folder 11)